A Guide to the Aldie Ruritan Records, 1972-2001
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Aldie Ruritan Records 1972-2001 1973-1999
Thomas Balch Library
M 003
1.65 cu. ft
The collection consists of secretary and treasurer's records from 1973-2001. It includes membership lists, attendance, and minutes as well some loose bank statements and other documents.
Aldie Ruritan
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Provenance
Gerald Keatinge, Aldie, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2004.0010
Historical Information
Ruritan is a national organization dedicated to "improving communities and building a better America through Fellowship, Goodwill and Community Service." The first Ruritan Club was chartered 21 May 1928, in Holland, Virginia. It is a civic service organization made up of local clubs in small towns and rural communities. Sixteen members are required to form a Ruritan club, usually with the assistance of an existing club. The name "Ruritan" was suggested by Daisy Nurney, a reporter for the Norfolk Virginian-Pilot newspaper. The word is a combination of the Latin word for open country "ruri" and small town "tan," interpreted as pertaining to rural and small town life.
Aldie Ruritan of Aldie, VA was formed in January 1952 with Clay Wood of Nokesville, VA, district governor of Ruritan, as first speaker. Officers included Edwin Skinner, President, A. L. Hutton, Vice President, Jim Taylor, Secretary, Jack Hutchison, Treasurer, John diZerega, Sergeant-at-Arms, and the Rev. Albert Fritter, Chaplain. The first meeting was held at Aldie High School
Excerpts from Aldie Ruritan Minutes from January 1973 through December 1993, as abstracted by Wynne Saffer, include: donations to Little League, Cub Scouts, George C. Marshall Fund, and Aldie Fire Department, dress code, ladies night, purchase of a flag, authorization to build two pit privies on the Little League diamond, many "delicious" dinners and picnics, sponsorship of Aldie Harvest Festival and many speakers of local interest.
Scope and Content
The collection covers 1973-2001 and includes secretarial and treasurer records; however, not every year includes all record types. Secretarial records were kept in a book provided by the national office, "Official Secretary's Book," and include attendance, membership lists, minutes, invitations to membership, correspondence, and other items of interest to members. Most financial records were kept in a book provided by the national office, "Official Treasurer's Book." However, there are loose bank statements, IRS forms, cancelled checks and bond records.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Saffer, Wynne -- excerpts from minutes
Loudoun Times Mirror, January 31, 1952, pg. 1
www.ruritan.org
Other Finding Aid
None
Related Material
None
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Secretary Records, 1973
  - Secretary and Treasurer Records, 1974
  - Secretary Records, 1975
  - Secretary and Treasurer Records, 1976
  - Secretary Records, 1977
  - Secretary Records, 1978
  - Secretary Records, 1979
  - Secretary Records, 1980
  - Secretary Records, 1981
- (Box 2)
  - Secretary Records, 1982
  - Secretary Records, 1983
  - Secretary and Treasurer Records, 1984
  - Secretary and Treasurer Records, 1985
  - Secretary and Treasurer Records, 1986
  - Secretary and Treasurer Records, 1987
  - Secretary Records, 1988
  - Secretary Records, 1989
- (Box 3)
  - Secretary Records, 1990
  - Secretary and Treasurer Records, 1991
  - Secretary Records, 1992
  - Secretary Records, 1993
  - Secretary Records, 1994
  - Secretary Records, 1995
  - Secretary and Treasurer Records, 1996
  - Minutes, 1996-1997
  - Secretary Records, 1997
- (Box 4)
  - Secretary Records, 1998
  - Secretary Records, 1999
  - Secretary Records, 2000
  - Committee List, 2001
  - Misc. Papers, n.d.
  - Ruritan Magazine (select issues), 1987-1993
  - IRS Forms, 1972-1975
  - Misc. Financial Records, n.d.
  - Cancelled Checks, Deposit Slips, n.d.
  - Financial Records, 1982
  - Financial Records, 1984
  - Financial Records, 1985
  - Financial Records, 1986
  - Treasurer Records and Financial Records, 1987
  - Treasurer Records and Financial Records, 1988
  - Treasurer Records and Financial Records, 1989
  - Treasurer Records and Financial Records, 1990
- (Box 5)
  - Treasurer Records, 1991
  - Treasurer Records, 1992
  - Treasurer Records, 1993
  - Treasurer Records, 1994